Guide to the Clara Lemlich Papers TAM.577
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Clara Lemlich Papers
1909-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Lemlich, Clara, 1886-1982
Margules, Rita
TAM.577
2 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes and 5 folders in a shared oversized flat box
Clara Lemlich Shavelson (1886–1982) was a leader of the Uprising of 20,000, a massive strike of shirtwaist workers in New York's garment industry in 1909. Later blacklisted from the industry for her labor union work, she became a member of the Communist Party USA and a consumer activist in Brooklyn, New York. The Clara Lemlich Papers (dated 1909-1992) contain correspondence; clippings about Lemlich; a file on her death and commemoration; photocopies of a 1916 diary written in Russian and of a diary from a trip to the Soviet Union; Yiddish language clippings; a few brief writings by Lemlich; memorabilia; and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Rita Margules in 2011. The accession number associated with this gift is 2011.044.
Arrangement
Papers are arranged alphabetically.
Biographical Note
Clara Lemlich Shavelson (1886–1982) was a leader of the Uprising of 20,000, a massive strike of shirtwaist workers in New York's garment industry in 1909. Born in the Ukraine to a Jewish family, she migrated to the U.S. in 1903. She became a garment worker and was elected to the executive board of Local 25 of the ILGWU (International Ladies' Garment Workers Union). After being blacklisted from the garment industry, she founded the Wage Earners League, a working class suffragist organization. In 1913, she married Joseph Shavelson and moved to Brooklyn. Around this time, she became a member of the Communist Party USA and a consumer activist in Brooklyn, New York. As an early and lifelong member of the Communist Party USA, in 1929, she founded the United Council of Working Class Women (UCWCW), which led a 1935 boycott of butcher shops to protest meat prices. The UCWCW later became the Progressive Women's Councils and was affiliated with the International Workers Order, a Communist-led ethnically based fraternal organization. After the dissolution of the IWO in 1952, Lemlich continued her activities in the Emma Lazarus Clubs, a Communist-led Jewish women's organization that she helped to found in the 1930s. Lemlich campaigned for unemployment relief, and later, tenants rights.
Scope and Contents
The Clara Lemlich Papers (dated 1909-1992) contain correspondence, including with Morris Schappes; clippings about Lemlich; a file on her death and commemoration including several issues of Jewish Currents; photocopies of a 1916 diary written in Russian and of a diary from a trip to the Soviet Union; notebooks; several topical files, including one on the Meat Boycott of 1935; Yiddish language clippings; a few brief writings by Lemlich; union membership cards; and memorabilia including two buttons featuring Lemlich and printed ephemera from the Emma Lazarus Clubs. The collection also includes photographs, principally of Lemlich and her family; and a few images from public events, some apparently dating to the 19th century.
Notebooks; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Community organization -- New York (N.Y.); Jewish communists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Lemlich, Clara, 1886-1982; Emma Lazarus Federation of Jewish Women's Clubs; Schappes, Morris U. (Morris Urman), 1907-2004; Margules, Rita
- "Clara Lemlich: The Story of Half a Century" by Naomi Barko, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence re: Lemlich, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence: Joseph Shavelson, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Diary in Russian (photocopy), 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Clippings re: Clara Lemlich, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Lemlich Correspondence (includes Morris Schappes), 1948-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence: Grandchildren, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Death, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 50th Birthday Telegrams, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Emma Lazarus Clubs: Bread and Roses Too, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial Early Years, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Jewish Currents, 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Membership Cards (Progressive Organizations), undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Meat and Bread Strike, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letters, Personal (to Family), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- ILGWU Strike Clippings, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- ILGWU Pension Fund Letters, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Memorabilia, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Miscellaneous Clips and Ephemera, 1954, 1976, 1982, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 198, Folder 8-9)
- Notes on Trip to Soviet Union (photocopy), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- New York State Assembly Campaign - 8th Congressional District, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Postcards, 1908-1914, 1935, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Union Membership Cards, 1919-1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Yiddish Clippings, 1953, 1955, 1961, 1976, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6, Box Shared Tamiment 198, Folder 10-12)
- Yiddish Clippings: IWO Women Knitting Campaign, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Notebooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Writings, 1952, 1959, 1963, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photographs of Clara Lemlich and Family, undated (Box 3)
- Postcards and Photographs of Clara Lemlich, Friends, and Family, undated (Box 4)